Thank you for tuning in to my talk today about Lō‘ihi Seamount,
which is the youngest volcano of the Hawaiian Island chain.
My name is Thi Truong and I'm presenting
research that I have done with my collaborators
David Graham, Mike Garcia and Peter Michael.
To study Lō‘ihi, we must start with Hawai‘i.
If we orient ourselves on the south coast of Hawai‘i...
and move offshore about thirty kilometers,
we will see an underwater volcano
at about a kilometer below the sea surface.
This is Lō‘ihi Seamount. It is a young volcano with
two rift zones, which developed early in its history.
Lō‘ihi has erupted a diversity of lava types
despite its short life.
For these reasons, Lō‘ihi has transformed our understanding
of the earliest stage of Hawaiian volcanism
called the pre-shield stage.
In addition, the presence of tholeiite basalt flows
indicate that a shield transition has already occurred or is ongoing.
Shown here is a summary of the methodological approach
to collect basaltic glasses for geochemical analyses.
Shown on the right is a 3D scan showing the interior
of a glass chip, where vesicles, or vapor bubbles are visible.
These types of bubbles are composed mostly of CO2
and they are likely to host the majority of Helium, as well.
Early noble studies at Lō‘ihi have established that Lō‘ihi
has among the highest helium isotope values at a Hawaiian volcano.
This helium isotope value is believed to arise from the primordial
mantle input, that is, a deep mantle source which has obtained
chemical characteristics of an early Earth.
At the same time, significant variation in helium isotopes
results in values as low as 20 RA, producing over 10 RA
difference of helium isotope values.
Because Lō‘ihi is close to the hypothesized melting region
of the Hawaiian plume, its variation sheds light not only
on the lesser understood pre-shield stage, but on the present day
distribution of chemical heterogeneities sampled by the Hawaiian plume.
Some explanations for the lower helium isotope values at Lō‘ihi
include intrinsic variation within the plume
radiogenic ingrowth of uranium (U) and thorium (Th),
as well as atmospheric and seawater contamination.
The addition of recycled components such as subduction
crustal materials may also account for the signature.
Integrating Helium, carbon and water measurements of
quenched basaltic glass can be used to explore this hypothesis.
However, most previous studies at Lō‘ihi have focused on the
shallow summit region where the retention of volatiles
from the mantle is a concern.
An expanded study of Lō‘ihi's deeply erupted glasses is needed.
The objective of this study is to contribute a comprehensive data
set of coupled volatile measurements from over 40 basaltic glasses
collected from Lō‘ihi’s deep rift zone.
Basaltic glasses were chosen because they represent erupted
melt compositions.
Collection depths from 1300-5000-m beneath sea level means
that samples were erupted under relatively high confining pressure.
In contrast to the shallow summit, where gas loss is expected
to be more extensive, high pressure from the overlying water column
in the deep rift should promote the retention of magmatic volatiles.
The majority of samples from Lō‘ihi with published Helium isotope
data do not have values determined by both crushing and melting.
In this study, Helium, and CO2 contents were measured from both
the melt and vesicle components to compute total contents,
which were used to evaluate relative behavior and partitioning.
Water and trace element compositions were measured on
the melt components.
This dataset provides a means to evaluate the causes of
volatile and helium isotope variations at Lō‘ihi Seamount.
For the rest of this talk, I will be presenting results
to address the following questions:
Is there systematic variation in helium isotopes at Lō‘ihi?
Are CO2 and water contents heavily modified by degassing?
Does elevated CO2/3He reflect the addition of recycled materials?
And do trace element signatures support the addition of
recycled materials?
Local variation at a single volcano will be useful to apply
to the broader scale, say, of the Hawaiian Islands
or the global high 3He/4He reservoir in the deep mantle.
For the rest of this talk, I will be using the same color
coding to indicate composition within the sample suite.
These designations are based on the normalized major
element composition of each glass relative to its position
along the MacDonald-Katsura line and based on alkalinity index.
Within the South Rift zone of Lō‘ihi, alkali basalts
are shown in yellow
transitional basalts are shown in cyan or light blue,
and tholeiites are shown in red.
In the North Rift zone, three samples from the same dredge
are tholeiites. These are shown in orange.
Helium isotope values are within the range of previous studies.
If we focus in on the results of the South Rift,
we see that mean 3He/4He values for tholeiites and
transitional basalts are different.
Specifically, tholeiites are higher than transitional
basalts. They are different despite the fact that
they often have overlapping values.
This study does establish that the diversity of rock types
can be related to the diversity of helium isotope variation.
It is also notable that the North Rift tholeiites in this
study are higher in 3He compared to the South Rift tholeiites.
Moving on to carbon and water results, we see CO2
measurements vary greatly among Lō‘ihi deep rift samples.
Comparing CO2 to a trace element like Barium (Ba)
indicates that samples have degassed by 95 to 99%.
That is, the least degassed samples have lost at least
95% of their original carbon inventory.
Lō‘ihi samples are highly degassed, despite erupting
at great depths. However, water-potassium (H2O/K2O)
ratios suggest that dehydration has not occurred.
Multi-species element modeling with carbon and water
indicate that the least degassed samples correspond
to about 2.3 km equilibration depth.
To evaluate the extent of vapor-melt partitioning at Lō‘ihi,
we examined the CO2-He concentrations of the vesicles and the melt.
All of Lō‘ihi’s samples plot outside the equilibrium field
as indicated by Henry’s Law.
Vesicle-melt partitioning suggests that helium diffuses faster
into bubbles than CO2.
Another way to evaluate disequilibrium is to look at the CO2/3He ratio.
This ratio is said to be consistent across mid ocean ridge
and ocean Island basalt sources. Deviation from canonical
mantle ratios indicate potential recycling processes.
In our Lō‘ihi suite, we do see some elevated CO2/3He. This might
indicate recycled input due to elevated CO2.
However, our examination of vesicle-melt partitioning indicates
that non-equilibrium or kinetic degassing is likely to have occurred.
Combining our results from vesicle-melt partitioning and the
CO2/3He ratio suggests the preferential loss of bubbles
has led to the loss of 3He.
This bubble loss will then drive the CO2/3He ratio upwards.
Hence, the CO2/3He ratio may not reflect the source,
or recycled components. Instead, it reflects disequilibrium
degassing processes.
While integrated Helium-Carbon results may not support
recycled components in the Lō‘ihi source, some trace elements
are indicators of possible recycled material.
For example, we see slight positive anomalies in Nb and Ta.
Lō‘ihi is notable for its elevated Nb anomalies,
both in previous studies and this current study.
Elevated Nb has been attributed to recycled crustal materials,
for example, eclogite in the mantle.
In addition, Nb/U ratios, which are typically consistent
across OIB and MORB are actually elevated at Lō‘ihi.
This indicates the possible enrichment from recycled materials.
In conclusion, the study yielded a number of results related to
volatiles at Lō‘ihi.
Helium systematically varies between rock types within the South Rift.
Furthermore, the North Rift tholeiite samples have among the
highest 3He/4He measured for this whole dataset.
This suggests some spatial variability, at least in helium isotope
ratios between the North and the South Rift.
Another major result is that C contents vary widely at Lō‘ihi,
and this is due to variable degassing of at least 95% of
the least degassed sample.
Despite the loss of carbon, water loss has not occurred.
Integrated helium and carbon results indicate that preferential
loss of helium may occur by bubble loss and non equilibrium,
or kinetic degassing.
In addition, trace element signatures may support the existence
of recycled materials.
Trace element results indicate that high-3He/4He samples also
have positive Nb anomalies.
This supports the existence of recycled materials with primordial
material.
The trace element signature of Nb/U at Lō‘ihi is elevated compared
to global ocean Island and MORB sources.
This suggests the addition of enriched or altered material.
Overall, the study sought to incorporate volatile measurements
and trace elements of a diverse set of lavas from Lō‘ihi Seamount
to constrain primordial and recycled components in the mantle source.
I hope this talk has convinced you that local variation of a
single volcano can be used to understand broader scale processes
happening in the global mantle. Thank you for watching my talk.
I also want to thank my collaborators, and I want to thank the
session conveners: Val Finlayson, James Dottin, and Jabrane Labidi
for inviting me to give this talk. Thank you to everyone who
made this work possible, and I look forward to seeing you
in the live session on Tuesday, December 14th.
[Music]